A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Fellowship Program in Economic Development and Administration, Fellows Library FA1516
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Fellowship Program in Economic Development and Administration, Fellows Library
1959-1967
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA1516
1.6 Cubic Feet 4 boxes (3 letter document containers and 1 legal document container)
Scope and Contents
Reprints, reports, Ph.D. theses, and books created by Ford Foundation Fellowship recipients in Economic Development and Administration.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas. During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was transferred to RAC in 2019 by the Ford Foundation and ingested by RAC as Accession 2019:013.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged loosely alphabetically into one series:
1. Publications, Dissertations, and Journal Articles, 1959-1967
Economic development; Economics -- Research grants -- United States; Ford Foundation
- Publications, Dissertations, and Journal Articles, 1959-1967; 1
  Scope and Contents
  If stated on the report/journal article, the author's home institution is included in the additional description note.
  - Abruzzi, Adam - "Finmeccanica" Svizio Problemi del Lavoro - Tecniche Direzionali - Operativo della Sintesi Delle Prospettive di sviluppo Dei Sistemi Di Retribuzione, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Roma, Gennaio
  - Adelman, Irma and Frederick T. Sparrow - Linear and Piece-wise Linear Dynamic Programming Models - A Sensitivity Analysis, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Adelman, Irma - Simulation of Economic Systems, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Adelman, Irma - A Linear Programming Model of Educational Planning - A Case of Argentina, 1965 December 20 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Balassa, Bela - European Integration: Problems and Issues, Center Paper No. 18, Yale University, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bower, Richard S. - U.K. Dividends and Retained Earnings - More Reflections, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bower, Richard S. - Risk and the Valuation of Common Stock - Abstract, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bower, Richard S. and J. Peter Williamson - Measuring Pension Fund Performance: Another Comment, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bower, Richard S. (?) - Choosing an Investment Fund, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bower, Richard S. and Vance L. Nimrod - Commodities and Computers, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bower, Richard S., Richard D. Chase, William Gifford, and J. Peter Williamson - Computer Applications in Investment Analysis, Appendices I-VI, 1966 June (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Brunner, Karl and Allan H. Meltzer - Predicting Velocity: Implications For Theory and Policy, Carnegie Institute of Technology, Graduate School of Industrial Administration, Reprint No. 138, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Brunner, Karl and Allan H. Meltzer - The Place of Financial Intermediaries in the Transmission of Monetary Policy, Carnegie Institute of Technology, Graduate School of Industrial Administration, Reprint No. 136, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Chandler, Margaret K. and Leonard R. Sayles - Contracting Out, A Study of Management Decision-Making, Graduate School of Business, Columbia University, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Clarkson, Geoffrey P. E. and William F. Pounds - Theory and Method in the Exploration of Human Decision Behavior, Industrial Management Review, Volume 5, Number 1, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Cohen, Jacob - Sector Investment and the Availability of Finance, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Bowling Green State University
  - Demsetz, Harold - Consumer Experience, Its Effect on Brand Loyalty and on the Structure of Market Demand, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    University of Michigan, Grant No. 57-339
  - Day, Ralph L. - Methods of Estimating Distributions of Consumers' Preferences, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Pennsylvania State University
  - Day, Ralph L. - Simulation of Consumer Preference, 1965 September (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Day, Ralph L. - Systematic Paired Comparisons in Preference Analysis, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Fiedler, Fred E. - Group Effectiveness Research Laboratory: The Effect of Cultural Heterogeneity, Leader Power, and Leader Attitudes on Group Performance: A Test of the Contingency Model, 1965 August (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Department of Psychology, University of Illinois, Urbana, Illinois
  - Fetter, F. - The Economic Articles in Blackwood's Edinburgh Magazine, and Their Authors 1817-1853, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Hamada, Koichi - Economic Growth and Long-term International Capital Movement, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Yale University
  - Heller, Walter F. - New Dimensions of Political Economy, The Godkin Lectures at Harvard University, The Promise of Modern Economic Policy, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    University of Minnesota
  - Howrey, Philip - Technical Change, Capital Longevity, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Kaneda, Hiromitsu - Substitution of Labor and Non-Labor Inputs and Technical Change in Japanese Agriculture (2 copies), 1965 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Kaufman, Jacob - The Railroad Labor Dispute: A Marathon of Maneuver and Improvisation (2 copies), 1965 January (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Kreinin, Mordechai E. - Effect of Tariff Changes on the Prices and Volume of Imports (3 copies), 1961 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Michigan State University, Grant No. 60-332
  - La Force, J. C. - Royal Textile Factories in Spain, 1700-1800, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Lester, Richard A. - Implications of Labor Force Developments for Unemployment Benefits, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    Princeton University
  - Marcus, Matityahu - Capital-Output Ratios and Their Variations, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    Brown University
  - Maurizi, Alex - An Economic Analysis of the Dental Profession, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Stanford University
  - Maurizi, Alex - Empirical Evidence on Labor Supply: The Case of Dentists, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
    Brookings Institution
  - Mayer, Charles S. - Pretesting Field Interviewing Costs through Simulation, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    Dartmouth College
  - McKinnon, Ronald I. and Wallace E. Oates - The Implications of International Economic Integration for Monetary, Fiscal, and Exchange-Rate Policy, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - McKinnon, Ronald I. - Research Center in Economic Growth: Intermediate Products, Differential Tariffs, and a Generalization of Lerner's Symmetry Theorem, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - McKinnon, Ronald I. - Research Center in Economic Growth: Portfolio Balance and International Payments Adjustment, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - McKinnon, Ronald I. - Research Center in Economic Growth: Futures Markets, Buffer Stocks and Income Stability for Primary Producers, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Meltzer, Allan H. - The Demand For Money: The Evidence From The Time Series, Graduate School of Industrial Administration, Carnegie Institute of Technology, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Miller, Merton H. and Franco Modigliani - Some Estimates of the Cost of Capital to the Electric Utility Industry, 1954-1957, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - McCarthy, Michael D. - Embodied and Disembodied Technical Progress in the Constant Elasticity of Substitution Production Function, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Meltzer, Allan H. - The Demand For Money: A Cross-Section Study of Business Firms, Graduate School of Industrial Administration, Carnegie Institute of Technology, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Morag, Amotz - On Taxes and Inflation, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    The Hebrew University
  - Nerlove, Marc - The Stanford Institute for Mathematical Studies in the Social Sciences: A Comparison of a Modified "Hannan" and the BLS Seasonal Adjustment Filters, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Nerlove, Marc - The Stanford Institute for Mathematical Studies in the Social Sciences: Two Models of the British Economy: A Fragment of a Critical Survey, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Neter, John - Nonsampling Errors in Administrative Applications, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    University of Minnesota; Grant No: 57-338
  - Quinn, James Brian - Industrial Research and Development, Some Comparisons of U.S. and Western European Practice, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Radosevich, Ray - Experimentation in Joint Decision Making with Goal Conflict and a Complex Task, 1967 May 11 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    Carnegie Institute of Technology
  - Ranis, Gustav - Allocation Criteria and Population Growth, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Rosen, Sherwin - Short-Run Employment Variation on Class-I Railroads in the United States, 1947-1963, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    The University of Chicago; Grant: 63-300
  - Soltow, Lee - Toward Income Equality in Norway, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Stagner, Ross - Resolving Top-Level Managerial Disagreements, Business Topics, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Stagner, Ross - Theory and Practice in Corporate Decision-Making, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    Wayne State University
  - Stein, Jerome L. - The Nature and Efficiency of the Foreign Exchange Market, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Stein, Jerome L. - The Optimum Foreign Exchange Market, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Stein, Jerome L. - Oligopoly in Risk-Bearing Industries with Free Entry, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Stein, Jerome L. - The Rationality of Official Intervention in the Forward Exchange Market, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Stoner, James A. F. - The Effect of General Values on Cautious and Risky Shifts in Group Decisions - Abstract, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Summers, Edward Lee - The Nature and Use of Accounting Data in Business Decisions, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    University of Texas
  - Tarneja, Ram S. and Kamla Chowdhry - India, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 60)
    Duquesne University
  - Tarneja, Ram S. - The Function of Organizing in the Managerial Process, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Thorelli, Hans B. - Salary Span of Control, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Vaughan, James A. and Avner M. Porat - Managerial Attitudes Towards the Role of Computers in Decision Making in a Large Metropolitan Bank, undated (Box 4, Folder 63)
    University of Pittsburgh
  - Weber, C. Edward - Intraorganizational Decision Processes Influencing the EDP Staff Budget (3 copies), 1965 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Yudin, Barry Elinor - American Skill Abroad: Its Role in International Trade, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - Zannetos, Zenon S. - Measuring the Efficiency of Organization Structures: Some Implications for the Control System of the Firm, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - Zannetos, Zenon S. - Toward a Functional Accounting System, Part I: Accounting Variances and Statistical Variance Analysis, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 67)
    Massachusetts Institute of Technology
  - Zannetos, Zenon S. - Measurement in Accounting: Scope and Setting, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Zannetos, Zenon S. - Theoretical Factors Affecting the Long-term Charter Rate for Tankers in the Long Run and Suggestions for Measurements, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - PA #58-322 Fellowship Program in Economic Development and Administration, University of California (Los Angeles) - McElhiney, Paul Templeton - The Freeways of Metropolitan Los Angeles: An Evaluation in Terms of Their Objectives, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 70)